Register of the Leopold Tyrmand Papers, 1941-1985
Hoover Institution Archives
- WRITINGS, 1951-1985
  - Zly, 1956
    - Reviews
      - Italian, 1959 (Folder 4)
      - German, 1961 (Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, with English interpreter, 1957 (Folder 6)
  - "Sprawa Piaseckiego," Tygodnik Powszechny, Typescript, 1956. (Folder 7)
  - Siedem dalekich rejsow, 1957
    - Book's opening pages. Typescript and holograph (Folder 8)
    - Reviews from British press of translation of Seven Long Voyages, Printed copies, 1959. (Folder 9)
  - "Jan Adapter," notes for play, Holograph, ca. 1960. (Folder 10)
  - "Jeden dzien z toba," notes for film script, Holograph, 1960. (Folder 11)
  - Polacy czyli pakamera, play, Dialog, 6. Printed copy, 1961: (Folder 12)
  - Filip, 1961
    - Book review, Tygodnik Powszechny, 1962 (Folder 13)
    - Book synopsis in English, Typescript, ca. 1972. (Folder 14)
  - "Naczelnik," comedy in three acts, 1962
    - Notes. Holograph. (Folder 15)
    - Full text. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - "Pewnosc i zaufanie," political play, 1962
    - Notes. Holograph (Folder 17)
    - Opening act. Typescript (Folder 18)
  - "La Feta," novel, 1962
    - Notes. Holograph (Folder 19)
    - Two opening pages. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Niebo," film script, 1963
    - Notes. Holograph (Folder 21)
    - Full text. Typescript (Folder 22)
    - Synopsis in English, 1967 (Folder 23)
    - Contract with film agent, 1967 (Folder 24)
    - Full text in English, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 25)
  - "Stasia," film script, 1964
    - Notes. Holograph (Folder 26)
    - Full text. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - "PL? Ach ja, Polen," Die Zeit, May 28, 1965
    - Printed copy (Folder 28)
    - Correspondence (Folder 29)
  - "Uwagi o turystyce czyli wstep do apokalipsy nadmiaru," article, written on request of German magazine, Typescript, 1966 (Folder 30)
  - Zycie towarzyskie i uczuciowe, Paris, 1967
    - Synopsis in typescript, 1959 (Folder 31)
    - Polish publisher's comments on submitted synopsis, Typescript, 1964. (Folder 32)
    - Contract with Kultura publisher, 1967 (Folder 33)
    - Book synopsis in English, French, and Polish, 1967 (Folder 34)
    - Promotional material in German, 1967 (Folder 35)
    - Press reviews, 1967-1968 (Folder 36)
    - Typescript of radio broadcast reviewing book, 1967 (Folder 37)
    - "High society and sentimental life," English translation, Typescript, early 70s. (Folder 38)
  - "Masculine-Feminine," film review, Typescript, 1967. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - "Hier gibt's nur eines-davonlaufen," Die Zeit, Printed copy, April 22, 1967. (Folder 2)
  - "From East Europe: The Dangerous Games Intellectuals Play," Interplay, Printed copy, 1968. (Folder 3)
  - "The Poles Intervene In Purely Polish Matter," The Reporter, Printed copy, April 4, 1968. (Folder 4)
  - "A European from America in Europe," New Yorker, Dec. 1968
    - Typescript (Folder 5)
    - Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Clasa de sus in Estul European," Vocea Libertatis, Printed copy, April, 1968. (Folder 7)
  - "The Yevtushenko Case: The Blue Fox is Tamed," The Reporter, Printed copy, May 1968. (Folder 8)
  - "The Yevtushenko Case," Typescript, 1968. (Folder 9)
  - "Huck Finn in Poland," The New Leader, April, 1968 review of Ferdydurke by W.Gombrowicz. Printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Russian Interpreter," review of book by Michael Frayn, Typescript, ca. 1968. (Folder 11)
  - Tyrmand's trip to Israel
    - "Polityka Polski wobec Izraela," unidentified Polish language Israeli weekly, Printed copy, ca. 1968. (Folder 12)
    - "W szponach metafizyki," unidentified Polish language magazine Israeli weekly, Printed copy, ca. 1968. (Folder 13)
    - Jews and Poland, Holograph, 1968. (Folder 14)
    - Synopsis of Tyrmand's appeal concerning antisemitism, in German, Typescript, 1968. (Folder 15)
    - "From an Israeli notebook," printed copy, Congress Bi-Weekly, March 10, 1969
      - Two edited versions of typescript (Folder 16)
      - Printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "Revolution and related matters," New Yorker, August 16, 1969
    - Typescript (Folder 18)
    - Page proofs (Folder 19)
    - Printed copy (Folder 20)
    - French translation in Ecrits de Paris, 1970 (Folder 21)
  - Notebook of a dilettante, article series,; book, 1968-1969 1970
    - Page proofs of articles published in New Yorker, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence from readers (Folder 2)
    - Reprints of New Yorker article in daily newspapers, 1968-1969 (Folder 3)
    - Syndicated weekly column, Typescripts., 1970-1971. (Folder 4)
    - Book contract with McMillan for collection of essays entitled "Notebook of a dilettante," (Folder 5)
    - Edited final copy of complete typescript (Folder 6)
    - Lists of book recipients as suggested by Tyrmand, 1970 (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence related to book from general public, 1970 (Folder 8)
    - Newsweek review, April 6, 1970 (Folder 9)
    - Correspondence related to Newsweek review (Folder 10)
    - Press reviews, U.S., 1970 (Folder 11)
    - Z notatnika dyletanta, Polish translation, n.d.
      - Typescript of 3 opening pages (Folder 12)
      - Reviews from Polish emigre press, 1970 (Folder 13)
  - Explorations in Freedom, 1970
    - "A cocktail party," book chapter. Typescript (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Transcript of radio broadcast reviewing book, 1970 (Folder 2)
  - Kultura Essays, 1970
    - Contract with publisher, 1968 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence related to editorial process, 1968-1970 (Folder 4)
    - Editor's note and Introduction, Edited typescript, 1969. (Folder 5)
    - "Personal score," book chapter, Typescript, 1969. (Folder 6)
    - Press reviews, 1970-1972 (Folder 7)
  - New weekly column, Typescripts, 1970-1972. (Folder 8)
  - "Won," Kultura, On Gombrowicz and Iwaszkiewicz. Typescript, 1970. (Folder 9)
  - "Permissiveness and Rectitude," New Yorker, Page proofs and final typescript, Feb. 28, 1970. (Folder 10)
  - Uncompleted article for Wall Street Journal, Clippings and notes, 1970. (Folder 11)
  - "Polish power," New Horizon, Printed copy, ca. 1970. (Folder 12)
  - "On fascism," article commissioned by Time magazine, 3 edited typescripts, 1970. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - "Revolutionaries: European vs. American," New York Times Magazine, Feb. 15, 1970
    - Printed copy (Folder 2)
    - Readers response (Folder 3)
  - "Tankar om det seksuelle frilynde," Norwegian translation of Tyrmand's article on sexual freedom, Syn og Segn, 1. Printed copy, 1971: (Folder 4)
  - "Notes on the Communist Life," New Yorker, Page proofs, Sept-Oct. 1971. (Folder 5)
  - "Thunderbolting the Corporate State," Interplay, Review of Ch. Reich's book Greening of America. Printed copy, 1971. (Folder 6)
  - "Russians," film script, 1971
    - Clippings. Holograph notes (Folder 7)
    - "The Possibilities of Coexistence," synopsis under film's original title. Typescript (Folder 8)
    - Full text in two edited copies. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "Nine Mini-Treatises on America," Encounter, Printed copy, February 1972. (Folder 10)
  - "On Opposing Communism," The Atlantic, May 1972
    - Printed copy (Folder 11)
    - Correspondence from readers (Folder 12)
  - "Oppositionelle a la Jewtushenko," Die Welt, Printed copy, October 14, 1972. (Folder 13)
  - "Paul and Virginia," authorship under assumed name of Sarah Novak. Novel, Final typescript, 1972. (Folder 14)
  - Rosa Luxemburg Contraceptive Cooperative, 1972
    - Correspondence with book publisher, 1971-1980 (Folder 15)
    - Title pages, trial printing, 1972 (Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, marketing campaign, 1972 (Folder 17)
    - Promotional material, Brochures, clippings, 1972. (Folder 18)
    - Press reviews, 1972-1973 (Folder 19)
  - "Cywilizacja komunizmu," press reviews. Printed copy, 1972 (Folder 20)
  - Ethnic controversy
    - "Siricas and Jaworskis," New York Times, Typescript and printed copy, April 3, 1974. (Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, readers response, polemizing article (Folder 22)
  - "The Yellow Pad," semi-biographical essay, Typescript, 1974. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Untitled article on Ford affair written for Kultura, Typescript, April 1974. (Folder 2)
  - Novel or play with Mr. Finegold as main character, Holograph notes, 1975. (Folder 3)
  - "Bowery," novel, Holograph notes, 1975. (Folder 4)
  - Tu w Ameryce pamphlet on status of Poles in U.S., 1976
    - Page proofs (Folder 5)
    - Pamphlet. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - Rockford Papers, first issue in series with Tyrmand's article "Our civilizaton," Typescript and printed copy, Oct. 1976. (Folder 7)
  - "Shepherds in Nylon Raincoats," travel essay, Edited typescripts, 1977. (Folder 8)
  - Chronicles of Culture, 1977
    - First issues of monthly magazine with Tyrmand's introduction, article on Rockford Institute, Printed copy, Sept. 1977. (Folder 9)
    - Final copies of articles, Typescripts, 1978-1980. (Folder 10)
    - Collection of articles and notes for monthly column "Prudent conservative," Typescripts and holographs, 1983-1984. (Folder 11)
  - Media Shangri-la, collection of essays on media, 1978
    - Collection of articles Tyrmand's authorship, Page proofs and clippings, 1976-1978. (Folder 12)
    - Final copy of typescript, 1878 (Folder 13)
    - Reprint of chapters in pamphlet, 1975 (Folder 14)
    - Press review, 1976 (Folder 15)
  - Correspondence from New York. Series of articles for Polish emigre magazine or radio program, Typescripts, ca.1977. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "On Culture. A Conservative Manifesto," political program, Typescript, 1979. (Folder 2)
  - "Church and State in Post-War Poland," political essay, Typescript, ca. 1980. (Folder 3)
  - "Homagium dla Kisiela," synopsis of radio broadcast for Radio Free Europe, Na Antenie, Printed copy, April, 1981. (Folder 4)
  - "What is happening in Poland," Wall Street Journal, Printed copy, July 14, 1981. (Folder 5)
  - "The Mandarin and Commissar," political essays on specific features of communism in China, "What do the Poles want?," political essay on reality of Post-Martial Law Poland. Both articles reprinted from Commentary, issue, and June 1983 issue and published as pamphlet. Printed copy, November 1982 (Folder 6)
  - "Notes on Polish Question," Policy Review, Printed copy, Spring 1982. (Folder 7)
  - "Mit rewolucji seksualnej," essay on sexual revolution, Nowy Dziennik, Printed copy, Nov. 25, 1982. (Folder 8)
  - "Poison of surrender has infected us since Yalta," essay reprinted from Chronicles of Culture in issue of Washington Times. Printed copy, August 31, 1984 (Folder 9)
  - "Die Frisuren des Mieczyslaw Rakowski," Kontinenet, no. 29, Printed copy, 1984. (Folder 10)
  - "Can conservatives overcome their image lag?," essay reprinted from Chronicles of Culture, in issue of Washington Times. Printed copy, November 22, 1984 (Folder 11)
  - The Ugly Beautiful People, 1985
    - Notes and clippings (Folder 12)
    - Edited typescript (Folder 13)
    - Final typescript of one chapter (Folder 14)
    - Edited page proofs of articles published first in Chronicles of Culture, and used again in this book (Folder 15)
  - "Letters to Amanda," unpublished epistolary novel written, ca. 1979-1985
    - Loose notes on various subjects (Folder 16)
    - Notes organized by author according to subject (Folder 17)
    - Notebooks (Folder 18)
    - Partial manuscript, late 70's (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Later manuscript, organized in chapters, early 80's (Folder 2)
    - First typed version with author's corrections (Folder 3)
    - 3 copies of one chapter, each with different corrections and additions (Folder 4)
    - Typed copy reviewed by editor with his remarks (Folder 5)
    - Final typescript after corrections (Folder 6)
    - Chapter 9 as package for publishers from author's literary agent. Typescript (Folder 7)
    - Article entitled "The New York Liberal" to be incorporated as chapter 3. Typescripts (Folder 8)
    - Author's brief description of book's literary form and its scope (Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with publishers (Folder 10)
  - "Sex as noise," unpublished book, ca. 1982-1985
    - Clippings on subject of sexuality (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Notes as arranged by author (Folder 2)
    - "Sex as Jumble," author's title of folder with sketches which originated idea of book, ca. 1982 (Folder 3)
    - First typescript in edited form (Folder 4)
    - Second corrected copy of typescript (Folder 5)
    - 3 copies of one chapter destined for various publishers or agents with their annotations and corrections (Folder 6)
  - Letters to editor of:
    - General, 1967-1984 (Folder 7)
    - Wall Street Journal, Printed copies, 1977-1981. (Folder 8)
    - New York Times, Includes Tyrmand's letter renouncing his Polish citizenship. Printed copies, 1968. (Folder 9)
    - Polish emigre press, 1968-1974 (Folder 10)
- SPEECHES AND LECTURES
  - American politics and media
    - Speech on American media, delivered in California, Typescript, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Speech on democracy and conservatism, Holograph (Folder 2)
    - Speech on liberal culture, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Speech on liberal journalism, delivered in Guadalajara, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - "The Media and the Present Danger," conference folder with biographical profiles of speakers (Folder 5)
  - Communism
    - "Third communism," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "Communism and us," Typescript, 1978. (Folder 7)
    - "Communism as another civilization," Holograph, 1978. (Folder 8)
  - Poland
    - "Lindenfelser Gespraeche, " report from conferences with Tyrmand's participation, on Polish-German issues. Printed copy, 1964-1971 (Folder 9)
    - "Polish intellectuals in the aftermath of the events." Typewritten transcript from seminar, Harvard, March 1968 1969 (Folder 10)
    - Speech on immigration, Typescript, ca. 1975. (Folder 11)
    - Speech on Polish-American ethic and political issues, Typescript., ca. 1976. (Folder 12)
    - "Wiadomosci i ja," speech on Tyrmand's cooperation with Polish-British weekly, Typescript, ca.1978. (Folder 13)
    - Speech on Polish church and its mission, Holograph, ca. 1981. (Folder 14)
    - Speech to Polish-Americans on traditions of Polish church, Holograph, ca. 1981. (Folder 15)
  - Rockford Institute
    - Nine sets of speeches on political and educational role of Rockford Institute, Typescripts and holographs (Folder 16)
    - Speech to staff at Rockford Register, local daily newspaper, and its relations to Rockford Institute, Holograph, ca. 1982. (Folder 17)
    - Speech on threat to values in America, and Rockford Institute's response to it, Typescript, ca. 1983. (Folder 18)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1967-1985
  - General. Includes folder entitled by Tyrmand: Polskie zaleglosci do wywnetrznienia (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - America
    - America as civilization (Folder 2)
    - American culture (Folder 3)
    - American politics in 60's and 70's (Folder 4)
    - Blacks and welfare (Folder 5)
    - Cult of celebrities (Folder 6)
    - Liberal culture (Folder 7)
    - Morals and manners (Folder 8)
  - Catholicism and church (Folder 9)
  - Civilization (Folder 10)
  - Communism (Folder 11)
  - Conscience (Folder 12)
  - Conservatism (Folder 13)
  - Crime (Folder 14)
  - Criticism (Folder 15)
  - Culture and cultural sophistication (Folder 16)
  - Europe, Western (Folder 17)
  - Fashion, garb, gossip (Folder 18)
  - Friendship (Folder 19)
  - Health and recreation (Folder 20)
  - Helsinki Conference (Folder 21)
  - Homosexuality (Folder 22)
  - Israel (Folder 23)
  - Jazz
    - Polish period, 1956-1965 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - American period, 1966-1985 (Folder 2)
  - Life, reflections on (Folder 3)
  - Philosophy and human fate (Folder 4)
  - Podhoretz, John (Folder 5)
  - Poland (Folder 6)
  - Press
    - Press, notes on (Folder 7)
    - Press, clippings on (Folder 8)
    - Press, hatred of (Folder 9)
    - Proposed Polish-American magazine, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Psychology (Folder 2)
  - Religion (Folder 3)
  - Revolution and counter-culture (Folder 4)
  - Rockford Institute (Folder 5)
  - Solitude (Folder 6)
  - South America (Folder 7)
  - Trip around Europe and America (Folder 8)
  - United States Information Agency (Folder 9)
  - Vietnam (Folder 10)
  - Writing
    - Writers and writing (Folder 11)
    - Writers, Polish (Folder 12)
- NEWSPAPERS AND MAGAZINES, 1967-1984
  - Wiadomosci, London, Polish emigre weekly, various issues, 1967-1981. (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Collection of various Polish-American newspapers, 1969-1984 (Folder 14)
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - 4 photos of Leopold Tyrmand, 1970 (Envelope A)
  - 1 photo of John A. Howard, undated (Envelope B)
  - 1 photo of drawing by Zbginiew Fitz, undated (Envelope C)
  - 5 photos of New Orleans jazz clubs, undated (Envelope D)